Richard McDermott Miller
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Richard McDermott Miller papers
1962-2001
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Miller, Richard McDermott
3.4 linear feet
The papers of sculptor Richard McDermott Miller measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2001. The papers document his work as an artist and teacher in New York City through biographical material, financial and business records, writings, subject files, and correspondence. His personal records about the National Academy of Design, of which he was an active member and president, are included.
Provenance
The papers were donated by Richard McDermott Miller to the Archives of American Art in 2001.
Related Material
The holdings of the Archives of American Art include additional photographs of Miller among the Louise Finklestein papers, circa 1944-2000, and sound tapes and partial transcripts of the Alliance of Figurative Artists lectures and panel discussions, 1969-1970, in which Miller participated.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Richard McDermott Miller (1922-2004) was a sculptor and educator in New York, NY. Miller was born Richard Alan Miller in 1922. After studying at the Cleveland Institute of Art in the 1940s, Miller returned to his home town of New Philadelphia, Ohio, to work in the family plaque business.
At the age of 40, he and his wife, Gloria Bley Miller, moved to New York City. This transition is the focus of Miller's posthumously published autobiography, Heading for New York: A Sculptor's Journey. Upon arriving in New York, Miller began using McDermott (his mother's maiden name) as his middle name.
Countering prevailing tastes, Miller abandoned the popular abstract style to explore the human form. In addition to executing portraits and medals, his primary focus was the nude female figure. He worked with live models, creating sculpture in clay or wax, often casting in bronze. Because of his dedication to naturalistic work, Miller became known as the "Figure Sculptor of SoHo." Miller completed several large-scale commissions for public spaces across the country. He taught sculpture at Queens College, and, with his wife, wrote the textbook Figure Sculpture in Wax and Plaster.
In New York, Miller was a prominent presence among the city's sculpture organizations, writing many letters to newspapers demanding proper recognition for sculptors. He was active in the Sculptors' Guild, and active member and president (1989-1992) of the National Academy of Design, and president (1997-2000) of the National Sculpture Society. Upon his death in 2004, he bequeathed his SoHo building to the National Sculpture Society.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor Richard McDermott Miller measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2001. The papers document his work as an artist and teacher in New York City through biographical material, financial and business records, writings, subject files, and correspondence. His personal records about the National Academy of Design, of which he was an active member and president, are included.
Biographical material consists of a resume and exhibition history, as well as notes and correspondence not involving Miller's vocation. Financial and Business records contain account books of income and expenses, records of his bronzes and a register of his work. Writings include speeches Miller prepared as he practiced for his teaching career. Also found are miscellaneous texts and drafts of unknown purpose, and musings on art. Artwork consists of one ink drawing.
Subject files reflect Miller's activities in New York City. Of particular interest is his pursuit of gallery representation, which led him to friendship and affiliation with Louis Pollack and the Peridot Gallery. There are also files relating to the Sculptors' Guild and the National Sculpture Society. Correspondence is mainly with other artists, patrons and collectors.
A significant portion of Richard McDermott Miller's papers relates to the National Academy of Design. Included are financial and legal records, correspondence, and minutes stemming from his involvement with the Academy. This series is especially rich for the period of his presidency, 1989-1992.
The small number of photographs found in this collection are mainly promotional in nature, and some are annotated.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1969-1997 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Financial and Business Records, 1962-circa 2000 (Box 1: 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1968-1969 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, 1985 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1962-2001 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear ft.)
Series 6: Correspondence, 1963-2001 (Boxes 2-3; 0.8 linear ft.)
Series 7: National Academy of Design Files, 1972-2001 (Boxes 3-4; 1.0 linear ft.)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1981 (Box 4; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Peridot Gallery (New York, N.Y.); National Sculpture Society (U.S.); Sculptors Guild (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects-Topical:
Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Art--Study and teaching
Names:
Pollack, Louis; National Academy of Design (U.S.)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1969-1997, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  This series includes Miller's resume and exhibition history, as well as a small number of personal notes and correspondence, such as a record of jury duty, a description of a dream, and a real estate advertisement placed in The Village Voice.
  - Resume and Exhibition History, 1974-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Correspondence, 1969-1980,undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Financial and Business Records, 1962-circa 2000, Series 2:; (Box 1: 0.4 linear ft.)
  Financial records consist of account books (7 volumes and one loose page) which record sales and expenses in the early years of his career. Some of the ledgers contain specific references and contact information for his models.
  Miller's three-volume register of his work in bronze describes 400 pieces and includes standard catalog information, casting history, and some sketches. A two-volume sculpture register (with reproductions of thumbnail size photographs) is a seemingly comprehensive list of all of his work through 2000.
  - Account Books (vols. 1-2), 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Account Books (vols. 3-4), 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Account Books (vols. 5-7; loose page), 1966-1968, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bronze Sculpture Registers (vols. 1-2), 1963-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Bronzes, Book One, #1 thru 75, Feb. 63-Mar. 66"
    "Bronzes, Book Two, #76 to 205 [1967-1979]"
  - Bronze Sculpture Registers (vol. 3), 1980-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "Bronzes, Book Three, #206-400 [1980-1999])"
  - Sculpture Register (2 vols.), circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Richard McDermott Miller-Early Sculpture (Before 1962)"
    "Richard McDermott Miller-Bronze Sculptures Numbered 1-411"
- Writings, 1968-1969, Series 3:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Writings of particular note are the speeches Miller prepared as he practiced for his teaching career. Miscellanous writings include texts (some with many drafts) of unknown purpose. Some seems to be press releases or textbook pages, but others record thoughts and musings on art.
  - Speeches (New School course), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Artwork, 1985, Series 4:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  This series consists of an unsigned ink drawing executed in April 1985 and annotated with the name "Eliza Decker."
  - Drawing, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Subject Files, 1962-2001, Series 5:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear ft.)
  This series reflects the artist's own organization of his professional records. Many focus on a single exhibition or project, and others reflect a continued relationship with galleries and consultants. Subject files may contain correspondence, notes, printed material, invoices, records of consignment, and photographs. These files mostly record Miller's professional activities and relationships with art institutions rather than interaction with individuals.
  - 615 Company, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alwin Gallery, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1964-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Art Consultants - General, 1982-1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Avnet Shaw, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - B. C. Holland Gallery, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bishop John Neumann Project, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Canton Art Institute, 1971-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Canton Art Institute/ Canton Museum of Art, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Canton Art Institute/Canton Museum of Art, 1999-1997, see also: Kent State University) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cavalier Galleries, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chess Set Project, 1967-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cleveland Institute of Art, 1966-1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Columbia Union National Bank, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Committee to Protect Public Monuments from Sandblasting, 1966-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dover Publications, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Duke University, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Feingarten Galleries, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - FFS [Friends of Figurative Sculpture] Gallery, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Figure Sculpture in Wax and Plaster (see: Dover Publications; Watson-Guptill Publications) (Box 1)
  - Foothills Art Center, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Galleries (Box 1)
    - General, 1962-1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Show Lists, 1962-1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Golden Swimmer Project, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hakone Open-Air Museum, 1985-1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hartford Festival of Lively Arts, 1965-1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Imprimatur Gallery, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - J. J. Brookings Gallery, 1986-2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Joe DeMers Gallery, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Johnson Atelier Technical Institute of Sculpture, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Kent State University, 1974-1983, (see also: Canton Art Institute/Canton Museum of Art) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Loveland Academy of Fine Arts, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Marcella Halpert Galleries, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Medallic Art Company, 1965-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Middendorf/Lane Gallery, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Models, 1963-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Modern Art Consultants, 1982-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Modern Art Foundry, Inc., 1964-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nassau County Museum of Fine Art, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Sculpture Society, 1977-2001, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - National Service Industries, Inc., 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Philharmonic Center for the Arts, 1989-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Parties, 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pearlstein, Philip (with transcript of dialogue), 1977-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Peridot Gallery (later Peridot/Washburn; Washburn Gallery) (Box 2)
    - General, 1962-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters, 1964-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Show Lists, 1965-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Statements, 1964-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Queens Museum, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Redevelopment Authority of the City of Reading, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, 1964-1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Schulman Investment Co., 1979-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Scottsdale Artists' School, Inc., 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sculptors' Guild (Box 2)
    - By-Laws, 1994-1995, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - General, 1974-1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Speakers Program, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sears, Roebuck and Co., 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Suburban Bronze Works, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "The Figure Sculptor of So Ho" Video, circa 1987, (1 VHS videocassette) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - University of Houston, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Voices in Bronze Project, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Watson-Guptill Publications, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Weatherproofing, 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1963-2001, Series 6:; (Boxes 2-3; 0.8 linear ft.)
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically, and chronologically within each folder. Files labeled "General" are reserved for correspondents with whom there is a very small amount of correspondence. Correspondence is characterized by a more familiar tone between Miller and his friends, patrons, and collectors. Some letters include photographs or clippings which are references in the text. "F-General" contains an illustrated letter from Larry Fadden.
  Additional correspondence is found among the subject files (Series 5). Biographical material (Series 1) also contains a small number of letters.
  - A-General, 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - B-General, 1963-1992 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - C-General, 1967-2000 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Columbia University, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - D-General, 1967-1992 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - E-General, 1969-2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Elliot, Robert K. and Ida Lee, 1986-1999 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - F-General, 1966-2001 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - G General, 1969-2001 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - H-General, 1967-2000 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Hale, Nathan Cabot, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Heckscher, William S., 1964-1973, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
  - Holden, Donald, 1985-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - J-General, 1965-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jones, Ron, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - K-General, 1966-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - L-General, 1964-1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Leeber, Sharon Corgan, 1981-2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Levine, Elizabeth, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - M-General, 1964-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - N-General, 1973-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - O-General, 1974-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - P-General, 1967-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Q-General, 1969-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - R-General, 1967-2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - S-General, 1969-1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Stroud Family, 1965-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - T-General, 1967-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - U-General, 1965-1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - V-General, 1967-1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - W-General, 1968-2000 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Y-General, 1967-1978 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Z-General, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- National Academy of Design Files, 1972-2001, Series 7:; (Boxes 3-4; 1.0 linear ft.)
  Elected to the Academy in 1977, Miller served on several committees and at various times acted as treasurer. He became president in 1989 and served until 1992. The bulk of this series relates to Miller's activities as president and the general business of the institution during that period, which was marked by a change in directorship.
  Records in this series are the remnants of Miller's engagement with the institution and are by no means comprehensive. General records - minutes, writings and correspondence - reflect his participating in Academy activities. Also included are clippings concerning the National Academy of Design and about topics of interest for personal research on issues regarding the artistic climate of the times.
  - Cain, Walter O., 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Legal, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Presidential, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Dobkin, John H., 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Donation Records, 1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Exhibitions, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Finance Committee, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Financial Records, 1988-1991, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Fundraising, 1988-1994 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Gallagher, Edward P., 1990-1992, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - General Records, 1972-1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - General Records, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - General Records, 1991, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - General Records, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - General Records, 1995-2001, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hutchins, Robert S., 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Investments, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Membership Information, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Middleman, Raoul, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Mission Statement Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Morse, Samuel F. B., 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Museum Board, 1998-1992, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - New York Academy of Art, 1983-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Portrait Program, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Mailings, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Publications, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Search Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Staff, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Teaching Philosophy, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's Records, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - West Coast Membership, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photographs, circa 1981, Series 8:; (Box 4; 1 folder)
  This series consists of photographs of sculptures that appear to have been used in promotional reproductions. Some are annotated.
  - Promotional Photographs of Sculptures, circa 1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)